4 One afternoon, a month later, Dorian Gray was reclining in a luxurious
armchair in the little library of Lord Henry’s house in
Mayfair. It was, in its way, a very charming room, with its high panel Wain
skting of olive stained oak, its cream colored freeze and ceiling of raised
plaster work and its brick dust felt carpet strewn with silk long fringed
Persian rugs. On a tiny satinwood table stood a statuette by Clon and beside it
lay a copy of Leon Nel bound for Margaret of valir by Clovis Eve and
powdered with the guilt daisies that Queen had selected for her device. Some
large blue china jars and parrot tulips were ranged on the mantle shelf and
through the small leaded panes of the window streamed the apricot colored
light of a summer day in London. Lord Henry had not yet come in. He
was always late on principle, his principle being that punctuality is the
thief of time. So the lad was looking rather sulky, as with listless fingers he
turned over the pages of an elaborately illustrated edition of Manon leco that
he had found in one of the bookcases The formal monotonous ticking
of the Louis quator clock annoyed him.
Once or twice he thought of going away.
At last he heard a step outside, and the door opened. “How late you are, Harry!” he
murmured I'm afraid it is not Harry, Mr.
Gray,” answered a shrill voice. He glanced quickly round and rose to his
feet. “I beg your pardon. I thought thought—” “You thought it was my husband. It is only
his wife. You must let me introduce myself. I know you quite well by your
photographs. I think my husband has got 17 of them.” “Not 17 Lady
Henry?” “Well 18 then. And I saw you with him the other night at the opera.” She
laughed nervously as she spoke, and watched him with her vague Forget Me Not
eyes. She was a curious woman, whose dresses always looked as if they had
been designed in a rage and put on in a tempest. She was usually in love with
somebody, and, as her passion was never returned, she had kept all her illusions.
She tried to look picturesque, but only succeeded in being
untidy. Her name was Victoria, and she had a perfect mania for going to church. “That
was at larrin Lady Henry, I think?” “Yes; it was at dear lrin I like Wagner’s music
better than anybody’s. It is so loud that one can talk the whole time without other people
hearing what one says that's a great advantage, don’t you think so, Mr.
Gray?” The same nervous Stato laugh broke from her thin lips, and her fingers began
to play with a long torto shell paper knife Dorian smiled and shook his head
I'm afraid I don’t think so, Lady Henry. I never talk during music— —at least, during
good music. If one hears bad music, it is one’s duty to drown it in conversation
ation Ah! that is one of Harry’s views,
isn’t it, Mr. Gray? I always hear Harry’s views from his friends. It is the only
way I get to know of them. But you must
not think I don’t like good music. I adore it, but I'm afraid of it. It makes
me too romantic. I have simply worshiped pianists— —two at a time, sometimes, Harry
tells me. I don’t know what it is about them. Perhaps it is that they are
foreigners. They all are, ain’t they? Even those that are born in England become
foreigners after a time, don’t they? It is so clever of them, and such a
compliment to art. Makes it quite cosmopolitan, doesn’t it? You have never
been to any of my parties, have you, Mr.
Gray? You must come. I can’t afford orchids, but I spare no expense in
foreigners. They make one’s rooms look so picturesque. But here is Harry! Harry, I
came in to look for you, to ask you something— —I forget what it was— —and I
found Mr. Gray here. We have had such a pleasant chat about music. We have quite the same
ideas. No; I think our ideas are quite different. But he has been most pleasant
I'm so glad I’ve seen him I'm charmed, my love, quite charmed,” said Lord Henry,
elevating his dark cresant shaped eyebrows and looking at them both with an amused
smile. “So sorry I'm late, Dorian. I went to look after a piece of old brickade in
ward Street and had to bargain for hours for it. Nowadays people know the price of
everything and the value of nothing I'm afraid I must be going,” exclaimed Lady
Henry, breaking an awkward silence with her silly sudden laugh I've promised to drive with the
duchess Goodbye Mr. Gray goodbye Harry you're dining out, I suppose? So am I.
Perhaps I shall see you at Lady Thorn's I dare say, my dear,” said Lord
Henry, shutting the door behind her as, looking like a bird of paradise that had
been out all night in the rain, she flitted out of the room, leaving a faint odor of
Frangipani Then he lit a cigarette and flung himself down on the sofa. “Never
marry a woman with straw colored hair, Dorian,” he said after a few puffs. “Why,
Harry?” “Because they are so sentimental.” “But I like sentimental people.” “Never
marry at all, Dorian. Men marry because they are tired; women, because they are curious:
both are disappointed.” “I don’t think I'm likely to
marry, Harry. I am too much in love. That is one of your aphorisms I'm putting it
into practice, as I do everything that you say.” “Who are you in love with?” asked
Lord Henry after a pause. “With an actress,” said Dorian Gray, blushing. Lord Henry
shrugged his shoulders. “That is a rather commonplace debut You would not say so if you saw
her, Harry.” “Who is she?” “Her name is cibil vayer Never heard of her.” “No one has.
People will someday however. She is a genius.” “My dear boy, no woman is a genius.
Women are a decrative sex. They never have anything to say, but they say it
charmingly. Women represent the triumph of matter over mind, just as men
represent the triumph of mind over morals.” “Harry, how can you?”
“My dear Dorian, it is quite true. I am analyzing women at present, so I ought to
know. The subject is not so abstruse as I thought it was. I find that, ultimately,
there are only two kinds of women, the plain and the colored The plain women are very
useful. If you want to gain a reputation for respectability, you have merely to
take them down to supper. The other women are very charming. They commit one mistake, however
however They paint in order to try and look young. Our grandmothers painted in
order to try and talk brilliantly. Rouge and espre used to go together. That is
all over now. As long as a woman can look 10 years younger than her own daughter,
she is perfectly satisfied. As for conversation, there are only five women
in London worth talking to, and two of these can’t be admitted into decent
society. However, tell me about your genius. How long have you known
her?” “Ah! Harry, your views terrify me.” “Never mind that. How long have you known her?”
“About 3 weeks.” “And where did you come across her?” “I will tell you, Harry, but you
mustn’t be unsympathetic about it. After all, it never would have happened if I
had not met you. You filled me with a wild desire to know everything about
life. For days after I met you, something seemed to throb in my veins.
As I lounged in the park, or stroll down Picadilly I used to look at everyone who
passed me and wonder, with a mad curiosity, what sort of lives they led.
Some of them fascinated me. Others filled me with terror. There was an exquisite
poison in the air. I had a passion for sensations.... Well, one evening about 7:00 I
determined to go out in search of some adventure. I felt that this gray moner
ous London of ours, with its myriads of people, its sorted sinners, and its
splendid sins, as you once phrased it, must have something in store for me. I
fancied a thousand things. The mere danger gave me a sense of
delight. I remembered what you had said to me on that wonderful evening when we
first dined together, about the search for beauty being the real secret of life.
I don’t know what I expected, but I went out and wandered eastward, soon losing my
way in a labyrinth of grimy streets and black grassless squares. About halfast 8
I passed by an absurd little Theater with great flaring gas jets and gudy play
bills A hideous Jew, in the most amazing waste coat I ever beheld in my life, was
standing at the entrance, smoking a vile cigar. He had greasy ringlets, and an
enormous diamond blazed in the center of a soiled shirt. ‘Have a box my my Lord?’ he
said, when he saw me, and he took off his hat with an air of gorgeous
civility There was something about him, Harry, that amused me. He was such a
monster. You will laugh at me, I know, but I really went in and paid a whole guinea
for the stage box To the present day I can’t make out
why I did so; and yet if I hadn’t— —my dear
Harry, if I hadn’t— —I should have missed the greatest romance of my life. I see
you are laughing. It is horrid of you!” “I am not laughing, Dorian; at least I'm not
laughing at you. But you should not say the greatest romance of your life. You
should say the first romance of your life. You will always be loved, and you
will always be in love with love. A Grand passion is the privilege of people who
have nothing to do. That is the one use of the idle classes of a country. Don’t
be afraid. There are exquisite things in store for you. This is merely the beginning.”
“Do you think my nature so shallow?” cried Dorian Gray angrily. “No; I think your
nature so deep.” “How do you mean?” “My dear boy, the people who love
only once in their lives are really the shallow people. What they call their
loyalty, and their fidelity, I call either the lethargy of custom or their lack of
imagination. Faithfulness is to the emotional life what consistency is to
the life of the intellect— —simply a confession of failure.
Faithfulness! I must analyze it someday The passion for property is in
it. There are many things that we would throw away if we were not afraid that
others might pick them up. But I don’t want to interrupt you. Go on with your
story.” “Well, I found myself seated in a horrid little private box, with a vulgar
drop scene staring me in the face. I looked out from behind the curtain and
surveyed the house. It was a tor affair, all Cupids and cornucopias, like a third rate wedding
cake The gallery and pit were fairly full, but the two rows of dingy stalls
were quite empty, and there was hardly a person in what I suppose they called the
dress Circle Women went about with oranges and ginger beer and there was a
terrible consumption of nuts going on.” “It must have been just like the palmy
days of the British drama.” “Just like, I should fancy, and very depressing.
I began to wonder what on earth I should do when I caught sight of the play Bill
What do you think the play was, Harry?” “I should think ‘The Idiot Boy’, or ‘Dumb but
Innocent’. Our fathers used to like that sort of piece, I
believe. The longer I live Doran the more keenly I feel that whatever was good
enough for our fathers is not good enough for us. In art, as in politics Le gr on
This play was good enough for us, Harry. It was Romeo and
Juliet. I must admit that I was rather annoyed at the idea of seeing
Shakespeare done in such a wretched hole of a place. Still, I felt interested, in a
sort of way. At any rate, I determined to wait for the first
act. There was a dreadful orchestra, presided over by a young Hebrew who sat
at a cracked piano, that nearly drove me away, but at last the drop scene was dra
drawn up and the play began. Romeo was a stout elderly gentleman, with corked eyebrows, a husky
tragedy voice, and a figure like a beer barrel Mario was almost as bad. He was
played by the low comedian who had introduced gags of his own and was on
most friendly terms with the pit. They were both as grotesque as the scenery,
and that looked as if it had come out of a country Booth But
Juliet! Harry, imagine a girl, hardly 17 years of age, with a little,
flowerlike face, a small Greek head with platted coils of dark brown hair, eyes
that were violet wells of passion, lips that were like the petals of a
rose. She was the loveliest thing I had ever seen in my
life. You said to me once that pathos left you unmoved, but that beauty, mere
beauty, could fill your eyes with tears. I tell you, Harry, I could hardly
see this girl for the mist of tears that came across me. And her voice— —I never
heard such a voice. It was very low at first, with deep mellow notes that seemed
to fall singly upon one’s ear. Then it became a little louder, and sounded like
a flute or a distant Hort boy In the garden Scene it had all the tremulous
ecstasy that one hears just before dawn when nightingales are singing. There were
moments, later on, when it had the wild passion of violins. You know how a voice can stir
one. Your voice and the voice of cibil vain are two things that I shall never
forget. When I close my eyes, I hear them, and each of them says something
different. I don’t know which to follow. Why should I not love her? Harry, I
do love her. She is everything to me in life. Night after night I go to see her
play. One evening she is Rosalind, and the next evening she is imag I've seen her
die in the gloom of an Italian tomb, sucking the poison from her lover’s lips
I've watched her wandering through the forest of ardan disguised as a pretty
boy in hose and dublet and dainty cap.
She has been mad, and has come into the presence of a guilty king, and given him
rue to wear and bitter herbs to taste of.
She has been innocent, and the black hands of jealousy have crushed her reed-like
throat I've seen her in every age and in every costume. Ordinary women never
appeal to one’s imagination. They are limited to their century. No glamour ever transfigures
them. One knows their minds as easily as one knows their bonnets. One can always
find them. There is no mystery in any of them. They ride in the park in the
morning and chatter at tea parties in the afternoon. They have their stereotype
smile and their fashionable manner. They are quite obvious. But an actress! How different an
actress is! Harry! why didn’t you tell me that the only thing worth loving is an
actress?” “Because I have loved so many of them, Dorian.” “Oh, yes, horrid people with
dyed hair and painted faces.” “Don’t run down dyed hair and
painted faces. There is an extraordinary charm in them, sometimes,” said Lord Henry.
“I wish now I had not told you about cibil vain You could not have helped telling
me, Dorian. All through your life you will tell me everything you
do.” “Yes, Harry, I believe that is true. I cannot help telling you things. You have
a curious influence over me. If I ever did a crime, I would come and confess it
to you. You would understand me.” “People like you— —the willful sunbeams of life—
—don’t commit crimes, Dorian. But I am much obliged for the compliment, all the same.
And now tell me— —reach me the matches, like a good boy— —thanks— —what are your
actual relations with cibil vain Dorian Gray LEP to his feet, with flushed cheeks
and burning eyes. “Harry cibil vain is sacred!” “It is only the sacred things that
are worth touching, Dorian,” said Lord Henry, with a strange touch of pathos in
his voice. “But why should you be annoyed?
I suppose she will belong to you Someday When one is in love, one always begins by
deceiving oneself and one always ends by deceiving others. That is what the world
calls a romance. You know her, at any rate, I suppose?” “Of course I know her. On the
first night I was at the theater the horrid old Jew came around to the box
after the performance was over and offered to take me behind the scenes and
introduce me to her. I was furious with him, and told him that Juliet had been
dead for hundreds of years and that her body was lying in a marble tomb in Verona.
I think, from his blank look of amazement, that he was under the impression that
I'd taken too much champagne, or something.” “I not surprised.” “Then he asked me if I wrote
for any of the newspapers. I told him I never even read them. He seemed terribly
disappointed at that, and confided to me that all the dramatic critics were in a
conspiracy against him, and that they were every one of them to be
bought.” “I should not wonder if he was quite right there. But, on the other hand
and judging from their appearance, most of them cannot be at all
expensive.” “Well, he seemed to think they were beyond his means,” laughed
Dorian. “By this time, however, the lights were being put out in the theater and I
had to go. He wanted me to try some cigars that he strongly recommended. I
declined. The next night, of course, I arrived at the place again. When he saw
me, he made me a low bow and assured me that I was a munificent patron of Art
art. He was a most offensive brute, though he had an extraordinary passion for
Shakespeare. He told me once, with an air of pride, that his five bankruptcies were
entirely due to ‘The Bard,’ as he insisted on calling him. He seemed to think it a
distinction.” “It was a distinction, my dear Dorian— —a great distinction. Most people
become bankrupt through having invested too heavily in the pros of life. To have
ruined oneself over poetry is an honor But when did you first speak to Miss cibil
vain The third night. She had been playing Rosalind. I could not help going
round I'd thrown her some flowers, and she had looked at me— —at least I fancied that she
had. The old Jew was persistent. He seemed determined to take me behind, so I
consented. It was curious my not wanting to know her, wasn’t it?” “No; I don’t think
so.” “My dear Harry, why?” “I will tell you some other time. Now
I want to know about the girl syil Oh, she was so shy and so
gentle. There is something of a child about her. Her eyes opened wide in
exquisite wonder when I told her what I thought of her performance, and she seemed quite
unconscious of her power. I think we were both rather nervous. The old Jew stood grinning at
the doorway of the dusty Green Room making elaborate speeches about us both,
while we stood looking at each other like children. He would insist on calling
me ‘My Lord,’ so I had to assure cibil that I was not anything of the
kind. She said quite simply to me, ‘You look more like a prince. I must call you Prince
Charming.’” “Upon my word, Dorian, Miss syil knows how to pay compliments.” “You don’t
understand her, Harry. She regarded me merely as a person in a play. She knows nothing of life.
She lives with her mother, a faded tired woman who played Lady Capulet in a sort
of magenta dressing rapper on the first night, and looks as if she had seen better
days.” “I know that look. It depresses me,” murmured Lord Henry, examining his
rings. “The Jew wanted to tell me her history, but I said it did not interest
me.” “You were quite right. There is always something infinitely mean about other
people’s tragedies Cil is the only thing I care about. What
is it to me where she came from? From her little head to her little feet, she is
absolutely and entirely divine. Every night of my life I go to
see her act, and every night she is more marvelous That is the reason, I suppose,
that you never dine with me now. I thought you must have some curious
romance on hand. You have; but it is not quite what I
expected.” “My dear Harry, we either lunch or Su together every day, and I've been
to the opera with you several times,” said Dorian, opening his blue eyes in wonder.
“You always come dreadfully late.” “Well, I can’t help going to see
cibil play,” he cried, “even if it is only for a single act. I get hungry for her
presence; and when I think of the wonderful soul that is hidden away in
that little ivory body, I am filled with awe.” “You can dine with me tonight Dorian,
can’t you?” He shook his head tonight she is imagen he answered, “and tomorrow night
she will be Juliet.” “When is she cibil van Never.” “I congratulate
you.” “How horrid you are! She is all the great heroins of the world in one she's
more than an individual. You laugh, but I tell you she has genius. I love her, and I
must make her love me. You, who know all the secrets of life, tell me how to charm
cibil vain to love me!
I want to make Romeo jealous. I want the dead lovers of the
world to hear our laughter and grow sad.
I want a breath of our passion to stir their dust into consciousness, to wake their ashes into
pain. My God, Harry, how I worship her!” He was walking up and down the room as he
spoke. Hectic spots of red burned on his cheeks. He was terribly excited. Lord
Henry watched him with a subtle sense of pleasure.
How different he was now from the shy frightened boy he had met in Basil hallwood
studio! His nature had developed like a flower, had borne blossoms of scarlet
flame. Out of its secret hiding place had crept his soul, and desire had come to
meet it on the way. “And what do you propose to do?” said
Lord Henry at last. “I want you and Basil to come with me some night and see her
act. I have not the slightest fear of the result. You are certain to acknowledge her
genius. Then we must get her out of the Jews hands. She is bound to him for 3
years— —at least for 2 years and 8 months— —from the present time. I shall have to
pay him something, of course. When all that is settled, I shall take a West End
theater and bring her out properly. She will make the world as mad as she has made
me.” “That would be impossible, my dear boy.” “Yes, she will. She has not merely art
consumate art Instinct in her, but she has personality also; and you have often
told me that it is personalities, not principles, that move the
age.” “Well, what night shall we go?” “Let me see today is Tuesday. Let us fix tomorrow
She plays Juliet tomorrow All right. The Bristol at 8:00 and I will get
Basil.” “Not 8 Harry, please halfast 6 We must be there before the
curtain rises. You must see her in the first act, where she meets
Romeo halfast 6 What an hour! It will be like having a meat tea or reading an
English novel. It must be 7 No gentleman dines before s Shall you see Basil
between this and then? Or shall I write to him?” “Dear Basil! I have not laid eyes
on him for a week. It is rather horrid of
me, as he has sent me my portrait in the most wonderful frame espcially designed
by himself, and, though I am a little jealous of the picture for being a whole
month younger than I am, I must admit that I delight in it. Perhaps you had
better write to him. I don’t want to see him alone. He says things that annoy me.
He gives me good advice.” Lord Henry smiled. “People are very fond of giving
away what they need most themselves. It is what I call the depth of generosity
Basil is the best of fellows, but he seems to me to be just a bit of a
Philistine. Since I have known you, Harry, I have discovered that.” “Basil, my dear boy,
puts everything that is charming in him into his work. The consequence is that he
has nothing left for life but his prejudices, his principles, and his common
sense. The only artists I have ever known who are personally delightful are bad
artists. Good artists exist simply in what they make, and consequently are
perfectly uninteresting in what they are.
A great poet, a really great poet, is the most unpoetical of all creatures. But
inferior poets are absolutely fascinating. The worse their rhymes are,
the more picturesque they look. The mere fact of having published a book of
second rate sonnets makes a man quite irresistible. He lives the poetry that he
cannot write. The others write the poetry that they dare not
realize.” “I wonder is that really so, Harry?” said Dorian Gray, putting some perfume on
his handkerchief out of a large gold topped bottle that stood on the table. “It
must be, if you say it. And now I'm off imag is waiting for me. Don’t forget
about tomorrow goodbye As he left the room, Lord Henry’s heavy eyelids drooped, and he began to
think. Certainly few people had ever interested him so much as Dorian Gray,
and yet the lad’s mad adoration of someone else caused him not the
slightest pang of annoyance or jealousy.
He was pleased by it. It made him a more interesting study. He had been always enthralled by
the methods of natural science, but the ordinary subject matter of that science
had seemed to him trivial and of no import. And so he had begun by
vivisecting himself, as he had ended by vivc ing others. Human life— —that appeared to him
the one thing worth investigating. Compared to it there was nothing else of any
value. It was true that as one watched life in its curious crucible of pain and
pleasure, one could not wear over one’s face a mask of glass, nor keep the
sulfurous fumes from troubling the brain and making the imagination turbid with
monstrous fancies and misshapen dreams. There were poisons so subtle that
to know their properties one had to sicken of them. There were maladies so
strange that one had to pass through them if one sought to understand their
nature. And, yet, what a great reward one received! How wonderful the whole world
became to one! To note the curious hard logic of passion, and the emotional
colored life of the intellect— —to observe where they met, and where they separated,
at what point they were in unison, and at what point they were at discord— —there
was a delight in that! What matter what the cost was? One could never pay too
high a price for any sensation. He was conscious— —and the
thought brought a gleam of pleasure into his brown agot eyes— —that it was through
certain words of his, musical words said with musical utterance, that Dorian
Gray’s soul had turned to this white girl and bowed in worship before
her. To a large extent the lad was his own creation. He had made him premature. That
was something. Ordinary people waited till life disclosed to them its secrets,
but to the few, to the elect, the mysteries of life were revealed before
the veil was drawn away. Sometimes this was the effect of art, and chiefly of the
art of literature, which dealt immediately with the passions and the
intellect. But now and then a complex person personality took the place and
assumed the office of art, was indeed, in its way, a real work of art, life having
its elaborate masterpieces, just as poetry has, or sculpture, or painting. Yes, the lad was
premature. He was gathering his harvest while it was yet spring. The pulse and passion of youth
were in him, but he was becoming self-conscious. It was delightful to watch him.
With his beautiful face, and his beautiful soul, he was a thing to wonder
at. It was no matter how it all ended, or
was destined to end. He was like one of those gracious figures in a pageant or a
play, whose joys seem to be remote from one, but whose sorrows stir one’s sense
of beauty, and whose wounds are like red roses. Soul and body, body and soul— —how
mysterious they were! There was animalism in the soul, and the body had its moments
of spirituality. The senses could refine, and the intellect could
degrade. Who could say where the fleshly impulse ceased, or the psychical impulse
began? How shallow were the arbitrary definitions of ordinary
psychologists! And yet how difficult to decide between the claims of the various
schools! Was the soul a shadow seated in the house of sin? Or was the body really
in the soul, as jordano Bruno thought?
The separation of spirit from matter was a mystery, and the union of spirit with
matter was a mystery also. He began to wonder whether we could
ever make psychology so absolute a science that each little spring of life would be revealed to
us. As it was, we always misunderstood ourselves and rarely understood
others. Experience was of no ethical value. It was merely the name men gave to their mistakes.
Moralists had, as a rule, regarded it as a mode of warning, had claimed for it a
certain ethical efficacy in the formation of character, had praised it as
something that taught us what to follow and showed us what to avoid. But there
was no motive power in experience. It was as little of an active cause as conscience
itself. All that it really demonstrated was that our future would be the same as
our past, and that the sin we had done once, and with loathing, we would do many
times, and with joy. It was clear to him that the experimental method was the only method
by which one could arrive at any scientific analysis of the passions; and
certainly Dorian Gray was a subject made to his hand, and seemed to promise rich and fruitful
results. His sudden mad love for cibil van was a psychological phenomenon of no small
interest. There was no doubt that curiosity had much to do with it,
curiosity and the desire for new experiences, yet it was not a simple, but
rather a very complex passion. What there was in it of the purely sensuous
instinct of boyhood had been transformed by the workings of the
imagination, changed into something that seemed to the lad himself to be remote
from sense, and was for that very reason all the more dangerous. It was the
passions about whose origin we deceived ourselves that tyrannized strongly over
us. Our weakest motives were those of whose nature we were
conscious. It often happened that when we thought we were experimenting on others
we were really experimenting on ourselves. While Lord Henry sat dreaming
on these things, a knock came to the door, and his valet entered and reminded him
it was time to dress for dinner. He got up and looked out into the street. The
sunset had smitten into scarlet gold the upper windows of the the houses opposite.
The panes glowed like plates of heated metal. The sky above was like a faded
rose. He thought of his friend’s young fiery colored life and wondered how it
was all going to end. When he arrived home, about half past
12:00 he saw a telegram lying on the hall table. He opened it and found it was
from Dorian Gray. It was to tell him that he was engaged to be married to cibil van
[Music]